{"tossups": [{"question": "This group ceded control of the Bug River to Lithuania at the Battle of the Blue Waters. The Stand on the Ugra River symbolically marked the end of this group\u2019s power, though it had earlier lost the Battle of Kulikovo to Dmitri Donskoy. This group once filled nine sacks with ears after defeating Henry the Pious at the Battle of Legnica [leg-neetz-ah]. This group was founded by Batu and forced Russia to pay tribute to the khan. For ten points, name this Mongol horde named for the color of its troops\u2019 tents.", "answer": "<b> Golden Horde</b> (accept<b> Kipchat</b> Khanate; accept<b> Ulus</b> of Jochi; propmt on the Mongols)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event, which inspired Michael Tippet\u2019s oratorio<em> A Child of Our Time</em>, caused many people to flee to the Restricted Sector for Stateless Refugees in Shanghai. Reinhard Heydrich sent a secret telegram with instructions for this event, which included the arrests of tens of thousands of men. This event began on November 9th, exactly fifteen years after the Beer Hall Putsch, and featured mass looting of stores and burning of synagogues. For ten points, name this 1938 attack on German Jews, named for the shards of glass that flew during it.", "answer": "<b> Kristallnacht</b> (accept<b> Night of Broken Glass</b> before \u201cglass\u201d is mentioned; prompt on it afterward)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This practice is often said to have begun in America with a Northampton County court case between Anthony Johnson and Robert Parker. John Punch is sometimes seen as the first American subject of this practice, which the<em> Code Noir</em>, requiring Catholic education, established in New France. A series of Virginia codes in 1705 defined this state as applying to anyone not belonging to a Christian nation. For ten points, name this practice that began with indentured servants of African descent.", "answer": "<b> slavery</b> (accept word forms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s suburb of Blachernae became the site of the royal palace after the rule of Manuel I. The Galata neighborhood near this city was populated by Italian traders and was the site of a namesake tower that controlled a large sea chain. This city, which was protected by the Theodosian Walls, was sacked during the Fourth Crusade and captured in 1453 by Mehmed II. The Hagia Sophia is in, for ten points, what city on the Bosporus, the capital of the Byzantine Empire?", "answer": "<b> Constantinople</b> (prompt on Istanbul; do not prompt on Byzantium)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One of these events caused the wreck of the<em> George L. Newman</em>, since the ship was unable to spot a lighthouse on Green Island. Some scientists theorize that Biela\u2019s Comet caused one of these events in the city of Peshtigo. Another event of this type was allegedly worsened after Daniel \u201cPeg Leg\u201d Sullivan let a group of animals out of a barn; that event legendarily began after one of Catherine O\u2019Leary\u2019s cows kicked over a lantern. For ten points, name this type of disaster that devastated Chicago in 1871.", "answer": "<b> fire</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<em>Sattriya</em> is among the classical forms of this activity in India in which the performer enacts a story. For ten points, name this performing art involving moving to the rhythm of music.", "answer": "<b> dancing</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This ruler integrated the laws of king Ine and Offa into his own codex, which became known as the Doom Book. This man established the southern boundary of the Danelaw after forcing his enemies into the Treaty of Wedmore, and he forced Guthrum to convert to Christianity after the Battle of Edington. Wessex\u2019s power was greatly expanded by, for ten points, what ninth century English king known as \u201cthe Great?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Alfred</b> the Great", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After Lyndon Johnson unveiled the Great Society at a speech at Ohio University, he more formally outlined its proposals at a speech at this university. The John F. Kennedy speech that first publicly outlined the Peace Corps was given at this university. The case<em> Grutter v. Bollinger</em> founded that racial preferences in this university\u2019s law school admissions did not constitute a quota. For ten points, name this university that moved to Ann Arbor in 1837 after originally being founded in Detroit.", "answer": "University of<b> Michigan</b> Ann Arbor", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This President\u2019s administration attempted to curb the arrival of communists by passing the Per Centum Act, which limited yearly immigration to 3% of a current ethnicity\u2019s population. After this man was nominated at the Blackstone Hotel in a \u201csmoke filled room,\u201d he routed James Cox in the general election. Secretary Albert Fall\u2019s sale of Navy land in the Teapot Dome scandal tarnished the legacy of, for ten points, what US president who promised a \u201creturn to normalcy\u201d in the election of 1920?", "answer": "Warren Gamaliel<b> Harding</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s winning commander allegedly stated \u201clet the boy win his spurs\u201d when he was told his son was under attack. An angered Count of Alen\u00b8con attacked his own Genoese mercenaries in this battle after heavy rain ruined their crossbows. This battle led Calais [kah-lay] to fall into foreign hands for over two hundred years. Like the later Battle of Agincourt, the winners of this battle used the longbow to render cavalry ineffective. For ten points, name this 1346 victory for England in the Hundred Years War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Crecy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "After Bob Hepple\u2019s charges were dismissed during this trial, he fled overseas. Judge Quartus de Vet presided over this trial, which listed Denis Goldberg and Walter Sisulu among the 11 accused. The main target of this event, who was arrested at Liliesleaf Farm, was sentenced to 18 years on Robben Island and a total of 27 years imprisonment before his release by F.W. de Klerk. For ten points, name this 1960s trial that convicted Nelson Mandela.", "answer": "<b> Rivonia</b> Trial", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man helped reinstate Phocis as the Oracle of Delphi during the Second Sacred War. This man faced a revolt in Miletus, which partly caused this lover of Aspasia to transfer funds from the treasury of the Delian League to his city. Thucydides recorded a famous funeral oration given by this man during the first year of a lengthy war against Sparta. For ten points, name this statesman who led during the Golden Age of Athens and the start of the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b> Pericles</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "In this year, Patrick Dunn helped organize a demonstration in Tompkins Square that police brutally repressed. The collapse of Jay Cooke & Company, which was unable to sell enough bonds in Northern Pacific Railway, helped trigger a financial crisis in this year, as did the passage of a Coinage Act that became known as the \u201cCrime of\u201d this year. For ten points, name this year in which an economic panic struck the US during the Grant administration.", "answer": "<b> 1873</b> (prompt on \u201c73\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A version of this document displayed in Palaestina Prima provided the source material for Eusebius of Caesaria\u2019s translation in his</b><em><b> Historia Ecclesiastica</b></em><b>. The city for which this</b> <b>document is named used to be called (+)</b> <em><b>Mediolanum</b></em><b>. Property was given back to the</b> <b>affected group of this document, who had been the subject of (*)</b> persecutions under emperors like Diocletian and Nero. Constantine created, for ten points, what edict promoting tolerance toward Christians?", "answer": "<b> Edict of Milan</b> (accept<b> Edictum Mediolanense</b> until \u201cMediolanum\u201d is read; prompt after)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>At this battle, a steamboat called the</b><em><b> Tigress</b></em><b> was taken to Crump\u2019s Landing to order a division leader to stand by. The</b><em><b> USS Tyler</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> USS Lexington</b></em><b> provided support for</b> <b>one side\u2019s movements along a river near the battlefield of this battle, where (+)</b> <b>P.G.T.</b> <b>Beauregard launched an attack from Corinth, Mississippi. Albert Sidney Johnston was killed at this battle, in which heavy fighting took place at the (*)</b> Hornet\u2019s Nest. A major goal of this battle was to cut off a railroad to Richmond that began in Memphis. For ten points, name this 1862 Civil War battle fought in Tennessee.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Shiloh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One country entered this war with Felix Schwarzenberg\u2019s declaration that \u201cAustria shall shock the world with the depth of its ingratitude,\u201d before turning on a former ally. This war was prompted when one nation sent the gunship</b><em><b> Charlemagne</b></em><b>, a violation of the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>London Straits Convention. This war, which featured an early engagement at Alma,</b> <b>culminated in the Battle of (*)</b> Balaclava, where Lord Cardigan\u2019s cavalry made a fateful charge. The Charge of the Light Brigade took place in, for ten points, what war fought on a peninsula on the Black Sea?", "answer": "<b> Crimea</b>n War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s speech at the University of Kansas stated that the gross domestic product\u201cmeasures everything except that which is worthwhile.\u201d This man, who cited a man who gave a \u201cripple of hope\u201d to South Africa in his \u201cDay of (+) Affirmation\u201d speech, wrote the book</b><em><b> The Enemy Within</b></em><b> about his efforts fighting the Teamsters in court. This politician was trailing (*) </b> Eugene McCarthy in the presidential primaries when Sirhan Sirhan assassinated him in Los Angeles. For ten points, name this man who served as attorney general under his brother John.", "answer": "<b> R</b>obert Francis<b> Kennedy</b> (accept<b> Bobby Kennedy</b>; accept<b> RFK</b>; prompt on Kennedy)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Gevork Vartanian discovered a plot by Ernst Kaltenbrunner to assassinate the attendees of this event. During this event, the Partisans were pledged support in their conflict with the Chetniks. After this event, a declaration was issued noting how the participants left it</b> <b>as \u201cfriends, in fact, in spirit and in purpose.\u201d The Sword of (+)</b> <b>Stalingrad was given as a</b> <b>gift during this event, where the details of Operation Overlord were discussed. This event marked the (*) </b> first time that Franklin Roosevelt met Joseph Stalin. For ten points, name this first conference of the \u201cBig Three,\u201d held in 1943 in the Iranian capital.", "answer": "<b> Tehran</b> Conference (accept<b> Eureka</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This battle began with skirmishes at Telnitz and Sokolnitz. The famous \u201csun\u201d of this battle lifted some mist during it, allowing Louis de St. Hilaire to advance. Prior</b> <b>to this battle, one side deliberately (+)</b> <b>weakened his left flank, only to later plug</b> <b>the gap with the arrival of Marshal Davout\u2019s III Corps [third core]. This battle was decided when one side was able to occupy the (*)</b> Pratzen Heights. For ten points, name this 1805 battle in which Napoleon crushed the combined forces of Francis II and Alexander I.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Austerlitz</b> (accept Battle of the<b> Three Emperors</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}